

Estefano Matías **Muñoz Moya**

PH.D. BIOMECHANICS STUDENT • EARLY STAGE RESEARCHER • DISC4ALL ITN MARIE SKŁODOWSKA-CURIE ACTIONS

setefano.munoz.moya@gmail.com | ★ estefano23.github.io | © 0000-0001-5222-4071 | ■ Estefano-Munoz-Moya

| ☑ estefano23 | 🛅 estefano-munoz-moya | 💆 @estefanoMunoz23

Presentation

I'm the Early Stage Researcher 14 - Ph.D. candidate in the European Project Disc4All MSCA-2020-ITN-ETN GA: 955735. I have a degree in Engineering Sciences with a mention in Mechanical Engineering (2017) and obtained my Master's degree in Mechanical Engineering (2020) from the University of Santiago de Chile. I have dedicated my previous research to two Chilean projects through experimental tests and numerical simulations. My current research focuses on systematizing multiscale modeling of intervertebral disc regularization during degeneration.

Education

Universitat Pompeu Fabra (UPF)

Barcelona, Spain

♦ DOCTORAL DEGREE | IN PROGRESS

Oct. 2021 - **PRESENT**

• Ph.D. Information and Communication Technologies.

♦ MASTER DEGREE | AWARDED | GPA: 6.9/7.0 | HIGHEST DISTINCTION

Universidad de Santiago de Chile (USACH)

Santiago, Chile

• M.Sc. Mechanical Engineering | Diploma Link

2018 - 2020

♦ BACHELOR DEGREE | AWARDED | **GPA: 6.2/7.0**

- Professional Degree Civil Mechanical Engineering | Diploma Link
- B.Sc. Mechanical Engineering | Diploma Link

Experience _

Research Work

⋄ Journal Reviewer

Jul 2024 - PRESENT

• CLINICAL BIOMECHANICS (<u>JCLB</u>) | <u>CERTIFICATE LINK</u> ♦ UNIVERSITAT POMPEU FABRA (UPF) | BARCELONA, SPAIN

Oct. 2021 - PRESENT

EARLY STAGE RESEARCHER (ESR) | DISC4ALL | DISC4ALL MSCA-2020-ITN-ETN GA: 955735 | PI: JÉRÔME NOAILLY

- Project: Training network to advance integrated computational simulations in translational medicine, applied to intervertebral disc degeneration.
- Numerical computational research on intervertebral discs under disc degeneration.
- ♦ Universidad Santo Tomás (UST) | Centre for Climate Change Research and Innovation (CiiCC) | Santiago, Chile

Oct. 2018 - Jun. 2021

RESEARCH ASSISTANT | CARBONATLAB | PROJECT PIA-ANID ANILLO ACT 172037 | PI: NELSON A. LAGOS

- Project: Interacting structure and function of ecological, mechanical and mineralogical properties of marine calcifiers: Shell carbonates as sources of bio-inspiration (Carbo-Nat-Lab).
- Experimental and numerical computational research on the shell skeleton structure from the Chilean coast, subject to climate change scenarios.

♦ Universidad de Santiago de Chile (USACH) | Lab. Biomecáncia y Biomateriales (BIOMATLAB) | Santiago, Chile

Oct. 2018 - Jun. 2021

RESEARCH ASSISTANT | PROJECT FONDECYT 1170608F | PI: CLAUDIO M. GARCÍA-HERRERA & DIEGO J. CELENTANO

- Project: Biomechanical Behaviour of Arteries from Chronic Hypoxic Animals: Experiments, Modelling, Numerical Simulation and Validation.
- Biomechanical characterization of arteries to observe adverse effects, such as hypoxia suffered by Chilean mining workers. In collaboration with the veterinary medical center of the University of Chile (FAVET).

Visiting Researcher

♦ TAMPERE UNIVERSITY (TAU), DECISION SUPPORT FOR HEALTH (DSH) | TAMPERE, FINLAND

Jan. 2024 - **PRESENT**

PROJECT: DISC4ALL | DISC4ALL | MSCA-2020-ITN-ETN GA: 955735 | PI: MARK VAN GILS | RECOMMENDATION LETTER: LINK

· Linking NFBC data with mechano-transport simulations of Intervertebral Disc (IVD), disc degeneration, and low back pain qualitative levels using the Disease State Fingerprint (DSF).

Oulu University (OULU), Research Unit of Health Sciences and Technology (HST) | Oulu, Finland

Nov. 2022 - Jan. 2023

PROJECT: DISC4ALL | DISC4ALL MSCA-2020-ITN-ETN GA: 955735 | PI: SIMO SAARAKKALA

• Clinical and Psychological data extraction from the Northern Finland Birth Cohorts (NFBC).

Teaching

$\diamond Pompeu Fabra University (\underline{UPF}), Information and Communications Technologies (\underline{DTIC}) \big Barcelona, Spain Communications Technologies (DTIC) \big DTIC Communications Communicatio$	
• PART-TIME TEACHER: Foundations of Physics PRACTICES.	Apr. 2023 - PRESENT
♦ Universidad de Santiago de Chile (<u>USACH</u>), Departamento de Ingeniería Mecánica (<u>DIMEC</u>) Santiago, Chile	
• Part-time Teacher: Engineering Drawing Theory.	Apr. 2021 - Aug. 2021
• Part-time Teacher: Strength of Materials Laboratory.	Apr. 2021 - Aug. 2021
• Part-time Teacher: Introduction to Mechanical Engineering Theory.	Apr. 2021 - Aug. 2021
• Part-time Teacher: Computational Mechanical Design Theory.	Oct. 2020 - Mar. 2021
• Part-time Teacher: Engineering Drawing Laboratory.	Oct. 2020 - Mar. 2021
• TEACHING ASSISTANCE: Introduction to Mechanical Engineering.	Mar. 2020 - Sep. 2020
• TEACHING ASSISTANCE: Strength of Materials.	Mar. 2019 - Aug. 2019
• TEACHING ASSISTANCE: Applied Mathematics.	Aug. 2018 - Aug. 2019

Publications | https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=930f_CMAAAAJ ______

PUBLISHED | MICCAI: MEDICAL IMAGE COMPUTING AND COMPUTER ASSISTED INTERVENTION | DOI

First Author | 2024

Jul. 2017 - Jan. 2019

· Pixel2Mechanics: Automated Biomechanical Simulations of High-Resolution Intervertebral Discs from Anisotropic MRIs

Published | Frontiers: Bioengineering and Biotechnology | DOI 10.3389/fbioe.2024.1384599

First Author | 2024

Unveiling Interactions Between Intervertebral Disc Morphologies and Mechanical Behavior through Personalized Finite Element Modeling

PUBLISHED | ORS: JOR SPINE | DOI 10.1002/JSP2.1294

Co-Author | 2023

· Cartilaginous endplates: A comprehensive review on a neglected structure in intervertebral disc research

PUBLISHED | FRONTIERS: CELL AND DEVELOPMENTAL BIOLOGY | DOI 10.3389/FCELL.2022.924692

Co-Author | 2022

• Immuno-Modulatory Effects of Intervertebral Disc Cells

• TEACHING ASSISTANCE: Thermal Systems (Thermodynamics II).

PUBLISHED | FRONTIERS: BIOENGINEERING AND BIOTECHNOLOGY | DOI 10.3389/FBIOE.2021.813537

Second Author | 2022

Biomechanical Characterization of Scallop Shells Exposed to Ocean Acidification and Warming

PUBLISHED | NATURE: SCIENTIFIC REPORTS | DOI 10.1038/S41598-021-04414-1

First Author | 2022

· Evaluation of remodeling and geometry on the biomechanical properties of nacreous bivalve shells

Conferences estefano23.github.io/work.html#conferences ____

VPHi Conference (VPHi 2024), University of Stuttgart.

US, Stuttgart, Germany

INTERNATIONAL | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK

Sep. 2024

• Pixel2Mechanics: Automated Biomechanical Simulations of High-Resolution Intervertebral Discs from Anisotropic MRIs.

50th International Society for the Study of the Lumbar Spine (ISSLS 2024), Quark Hotel.

Milano, Italy May. 2024

INTERNATIONAL | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK

· Unveiling the interaction between IVD local morphologies and mechanical behavior through a novel morphing process: A step towards per-

31st European Orthopaedic Research Society (EORS 2023), Minho University.

UM, Porto, Portugal

INTERNATIONAL | SPEAKER & POSTER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK | POSTER LINK

Sep. 2023

• Mining of biomechanical and geometry data of IVD FE simulations.

28° Congress of the European Society of Biomechanics (ESB 2023), Maastricht Congress Center.

UM, Maastricht, The Netherlands

INTERNATIONAL | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK

· A cohort of patient-specific and virtual finite element models of intervertebral discs and model validation

18th International Symposium on Computer Methods in Biomechanics and Biomedical Engineering (CMBBE 2023), Arts et Métiers Institute of Technology.

IAM, Paris, France

INTERNATIONAL | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK

May. 2023

· A cohort of patient-specific and virtual finite element models of intervertebral discs

XI Capítulo Español: Sociedad Europea de Biomecánica (ESB-ESP 2022), Universidad de Zaragoza.

UNIZAR, Zaragoza, Spain

SPAIN | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK

 GENERACIÓN DE UNA COHORTE DE MODELOS DE ELEMENTOS FINITOS DE DISCOS INTERVERTEBRALES ESPECÍFICO DE PACIENTES, CON EX-TENSIÓN A COHORTE VIRTUAL.

VPHi Conference (VPHi 2022), Universidade do Porto.

International | Poster Presentation | Certificate Link | Poster Link

TOWARDS A REPOSITORY OF PATIENT-SPECIFIC INTERVERTEBRAL DISC FINITE ELEMENT MODELS.

UPORTO, Porto, Portugal Sep. 2022

UPORTO, Porto, Portugal

International | Speaker Presentation | Certificate Link | Podium Certificate Link

TOWARDS A REPOSITORY OF PATIENT-SPECIFIC INTERVERTEBRAL DISC FINITE ELEMENT MODELS.

27° Congress of the European Society of Biomechanics (ESB 2022), Universidade do Porto.

1st Taulí Health symposium - ARTIFICIAL INTELLIGENCE, Investigación e Innovación Parc Taulí.

13PT, Catalunya, Spain

Jun. 2022

Apr. 2022

INTERNATIONAL | SPECTATOR | CERTIFICATE LINK

• AI for Health and Wellness

UPF, Barcelona, Spain

6th Barcelona VPH Summer School (VPH SC 2022), Universitat Pompeu Fabra.

May. 2022

INTERNATIONAL | POSTER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK | POSTER LINK

• TOWARDS A REPOSITORY OF PATIENT-SPECIFIC INTERVERTEBRAL DISC FINITE ELEMENT MODELS.

ULisboa, Lisboa, Portugal

INTERNATIONAL | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK

• TOWARDS A REPOSITORY OF PATIENT-SPECIFIC INTERVERTEBRAL DISC FINITE ELEMENT MODELS.

IX International Conference on Computational Bioengineering (ICCB 2022), ULisboa.

X Capítulo Español: Sociedad Europea de Biomecánica (ESB-ESP 2021), Universidad de Granada.

UGR, Granada, Spain

SPAIN | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK

Oct. 2021

• COMPORTAMIENTO BIOMECÁNICO DE LAS CONCHAS DE LOS MEJILLONES: DEGRADACIÓN DURANTE LA REMODELACIÓN DE LAS PROPIEDADES MECÁNICAS Y SISTEMA DE DEFENSA.

XL Congreso de Ciencias del Mar, Universidad de Magallanes, SCHCM.

CHILE | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK

UMAG, Magallanes, Chile, Virtual

• COMPORTAMIENTO MECÁNICO SIMÉTRICO DE LA RESISTENCIA DE LAS CONCHAS DEL MEJILLÓN PERUMYTILUS PURPURATUS.

11° World Biomaterials Congress (WBC 2020), University of Glasgow, IUSBSE.

Glas, Glasgow, Scotland, Virtual

INTERNATIONAL | POSTER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK | POSTER LINK

Dec. 2020

May. 2021

MECHANICAL BEHAVIOR SYMMETRY OF MUSSEL SHELLS AND NUMERICAL METHOD FOR BIOMATERIAL ORTHOTROPY DIRECTIONS.

2° Congreso de Estudiantes de Postgrado USACH (USACH 2020), Universidad de Santiago de Chile.

USACH, Santiago, Chile, Virtual

CHILE | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK

Nov. 2020

PERUMYTILUS PURPURATUS: SIMETRÍA DE VALVAS Y CARACTERIZACIÓN DE DIRECCIÓN ORTÓTROPA.

Congreso Chileno de Biomecánica y Biomateriales (CBIO 2020), Universidad de Santiago de Chile.

USACH, Santiago, Chile, Virtual

CHILE | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | ORGANIZER | CERTIFICATE LINK

Oct. 2020

• PERUMYTILUS PURPURATUS: SIMETRÍA DE VALVAS Y CARACTERIZACIÓN DE DIRECCIÓN ORTÓTROPA.

Congreso Internacional de Metalurgia y Materiales (CONAMET 2019), Universidad Austral de Chile.

UACH, Valdivia, Chile

INTERNATIONAL | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK

Nov. 2019

ANÁLISIS DE LA RESPUESTA BIOMECÁNICA DE PERUMYTILUS PURPURATUS ANTE ESCENARIOS DE CAMBIO CLIMÁTICO.

1° Congreso de Estudiantes de Postgrado USACH (USACH 2019), Universidad de Santiago de Chile.

USACH, Santiago, Chile

CHILE | SPEAKER PRESENTATION | CERTIFICATE LINK

Aug. 2019

• MODELOS CONSTITUTIVOS DE CRECIMIENTO APLICADOS A LA CONCHA DEL PERUMYTILUS PURPURATUS.

25° Congress of the European Society of Biomechanics (ESB 2019), TU Wien.

TU Wien, Vienna, Austria

INTERNATIONAL | 2 SPEAKER PRESENTATIONS | CERTIFICATE LINK | PODIUM CERTIFICATE LINK

Jul. 2019

- BIOMECHANICAL BEHAVIOUR ON SHELL CHARACTERISTICS (PERUMYTILUS PURPURATUS) ALONG THE CHILEAN COAST.
- NUMERICAL ANALYSIS OF THE BIOMECHANICAL RESPONSE OF OYSTER SHELLS SUBJECTED TO CLIMATE CHANGE SCENARIOS.

Courses_

The Human Digital Twin Summer School Barcelona, Universitat Pompeu Fabra (UPF).

Barcelona, Spain

TRAINING PROGRAM | TEACHER | CERTIFICATE LINK

Mar. 2024

· HandsOn: Patient-specific intervertebral disc modelling for biological stratification with clinical data.

7th Barcelona VPH Summer School (VPH SC 2023), Universitat Pompeu Fabra (UPF).

Barcelona, Spain

TRAINING PROGRAM | POSTER | POSTER LINK

May. 2022

• Poster: Towards a repository of patient-specific intervertebral discs finite element models. 6th Barcelona VPH Summer School (VPH SC 2022), Universitat Pompeu Fabra (UPF).

Barcelona, Spain

Training program | Teacher & Poster | Certificate Link | Poster Link

May. 2022

• HandsOn: Surrogate modeling of IVD simulation under physiological sports loading conditions.

TRAINING PROGRAM | STUDENT | CERTIFICATE LINK

Jun. 2021

• Transversal training of in silico medicine. Dictated by BCN MedTech, Virtual Physiological Human Institute (VPHi), and QUAES Foundation.

Structure, form, and function of calcifying organisms

CIMARQ UNAB, Valparaíso, Chile

POSTGRADUATE COURSE | STUDENT | CERTIFICATE LINK

Nov. 2018

Dictated by the academics Ph. D. Antonio Checa (Universidad de Granada, Spain) and Ph. D. Fabio Labra (Universidad Santo Tomás, Chile).

Memberships _

Virtual Physiological Human institute (VPHi)

Europe

STUDENT MEMBER | CERTIFICATE LINK

Sep. 2022 - **PRESENT**

· Membership UPF

European Society of Biomechanics (ESB)

Europe

Student Member | Certificate Link

Jul. 2020 - **PRESENT**

• Membership ID: 3263

STEM Preeschoolar USACH-DIMEC (Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics)

Santiago, Chile

MEMBER | CERTIFICATE LINK

Oct. 2019 - Sep. 2021

• Scientific popularization for preschool children with a gender perspective.

Awards

6th Barcelona VPH Summer School (VPH SC 2022), Universitat Pompeu Fabra (UPF).

Barcelona, Spain

May. 2022

BEST HANDSON | CERTIFICATE LINK

• HandsOn: Surrogate modeling of IVD simulation under physiological sports loading conditions.

Barcelona, Spain

SCHOLARSHIP | CERTIFICATE LINK

Oct. 2013 - 2021

• Full Ph.D. scholarship. EARLY STAGE RESEARCHER DISC4ALL ITN MARIE SKŁODOWSKA-CURIE ACTIONS

Government of Chile to study in University of Santiago de Chile (USACH).

European Union to study in Universitat Pompeu Fabra (UPF).

Santiago, Chile

 $\mathsf{SCHOLARSHIP} \, \big| \, \underline{\mathsf{CERTIFICATE} \, \mathsf{LINK}}$

Oct. 2018 - 2020

• Full Master scholarship. BECA ARANCEL

Government of Chile to study in University of Santiago de Chile (USACH).

Santiago, Chile Oct. 2013 - 2021

Scholarship | Certificate Link

• Full Undergraduate scholarship. BECA BICENTENARIO

Science Popularization _____

Science Festival - Festival de la Ciencia (FECI of PAR Explora RM Sur Poniente), Universidad de Chile

UCHILE, Virtual

Nov. 2020

• Science experiments for children.

Science Festival - 10° Feria Científica USACH, Universidad de Santiago de Chile

USACH, Santiago, Chile

EXPERT SCIENTIFIC COLLABORATOR | CERTIFICATE LINK

EXPERT SCIENTIFIC COLLABORATOR | CERTIFICATE LINK

Oct. 2019

· Exhibition of biomechanical tests for children.

Exhibition - Mollusca, espiral del cambio - CiiCC, Museo de Historia Natural de Valparaíso (MHNV)

MHNV, Valparaíso, Chile

EXPERT SCIENTIFIC COLLABORATOR | CERTIFICATE LINK

Oct. 2019

• Exhibition of the consequences of climate change in the oceans.

Exhibition - XII Fiesta de la ciencia y la tecnología (PAR Explora RM Sur Oriente), Universidad de Chile

PARQUEMET, Santiago, Chile

EXPERT SCIENTIFIC COLLABORATOR | CERTIFICATE LINK

Oct. 2018

• Exhibition of the mechanical properties of the mollusk shells subject to climate change scenarios.



Full name: Estefano Matías Muñoz Moya

BASIC INFORMATION

- Nationality: Spain & Chile European & American Passport
- Birth: 23th of September of 1994 | Santiago, RM, Republic of Chile
- email: estefano.munoz.moya@gmail.com
- Lenguages: Native Spanish | Advanced English

PROGRAMMING LENGUAGES AND SOFTWARE USAGE

- Programming lenguages: : Fortran | Python | Matlab/Octave | C/C++ | HTML |
- Software usage: In-House FEM Softwares | AutoCAD | Abaqus | Solidworks | Ansys | Inventor | Mathcad | Fusion360 | SAM | Latex | Arduino | Ubuntu | EDEM | GiD | InVesalius | Office (Word, PowerPoint, Excel, Project) |

References

Ph. D. Jérôme Noailly | ResearchGate Link, Principal investigator, ESR supervision, and project coordinator of Disc4All - Universitat Pompeu Fabra (UPF). email: jerome.noailly@upf.edu

Ph. D. Gemma Piella | ResearchGate Link, She lead the research areas of Medical Image Analysis and Machine Learning for Personalised Medicine in BCN Medical Technologies. She is also the coordinator of the Master of Computational Biomedical Engineering - Universitat Pompeu Fabra (UPF). email: gemma.piella@upf.edu

Ph. D. Mark van Gils | ResearchGate Link | Recommendation Letter, Principal investigator, Decision Support for Health supervision - Tampere University (TAU). email: mark.vangils@tuni.fi

Ph. D. Claudio M. García-Herrera | ResearchGate Link, Director of the Mechanical Engineering Department, Associated Professor, and Researcher - University of Santiago de Chile (USACH). email: claudio.garcia@usach.cl

Ph. D. Nelson A. Lagos | ResearchGate Link, Director of the Centre for Climate Change Research and Innovation (CiiCC), Associated Professor, and Researcher - Santo Tomás University (UST). email: nlagoss@santotomas.cl

Ph. D. Diego J. Celentano | ResearchGate Link, Full Professor and Researcher of Mechanical and Metallurgical Engineering Department, Pontifical Catholic University of Chile (PUC Chile). email: dcelentano@ing.puc.cl